## Baris Kasikci

 $Assistant\ Professor$ Electrical Engineering and Computer Science University of Michigan

 $4820~\mathrm{BBB}$ 2260 Hayward Street Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA +1 (734) 763-1560 barisk@umich.edu

http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~barisk

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is centered around building efficient and trustworthy computer systems. I build techniques to improve the efficiency of datacenter applications, provide systems support for heterogeneous computing platforms, verify the safety of complex distributed systems, analyze and fix failures, and improve the security of modern hardware.

1

## **EDUCATION**

## Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

PhD in Computer Science

Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Thesis: Techniques for Detection, Root Cause Diagnosis,

and Classification of In-Production Concurrency Bugs

Advisor: Prof. George Candea

#### Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey

Sep. 2002-Jun. 2006

M.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Sep. 2006-Jun. 2009 Thesis: Variability Modeling in Software Product Lines

Graduated with the top grade Advisor: Prof. Semih Bilgen

B.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Project: Embedded Target Estimation, Detection, and Tracking

Graduated with High Honors Advisor: Prof. Arzu Koc

#### AWARDS AND HONORS IEEE Micro Top Pick Honorable Mention, "Agamotto" 2021 NSF CAREER Award 2020 Intel Rising Star Award 2020 2020 IEEE Micro Top Pick Honorable Mention, "NDA" Google Faculty Research Award 2019 IEEE Micro Top Pick, "Foreshadow" 2019 Intel Faculty Award 2019 Jay Lepreau Best Paper Award, OSDI 2018 Intel Faculty Award 2018 Outstanding Reviewer Award, WWW 2017 Patrick Denantes Memorial Prize for outstanding PhD thesis, EPFL 2016 EuroSys Roger Needham Award for Best PhD. Thesis in Computer Systems in Europe 2016 Intel Corp. Software and Services Group, Grant 2014-2016 VMware Inc., Doctoral Fellowship 2014-2015 EPFL, Doctoral Fellowship 2010-2011 Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey, Master Scholarship 2006 - 2008FUNDING SRC Realignment Grant, 406K USD, PI 2021 NSF CAREER Award, 576K USD, PI 2020 NSF/Intel FoMR Grant, 180K USD (360K USD total), co-PI 2020 NSF FMitF Grant, 375K USD (750K USD total), co-PI 2020 DARPA AMP Grant, 600K USD (1.8M USD total), PI 2020 SRC Seed Grant, 50K USD (150K USD total), PI 2020 Intel Rising Star Award, 50K USD, PI 2020 Intel Faculty Award, Performance Debugging, 75K USD, PI 2019 Google Cloud Computing Grant, 5K USD, PI 2019 Google Faculty Research Award, 80K USD, PI 2019 Intel Faculty Award, Automated Performance Optimization, 75K USD, PI 2018 Michigan College of Engineering Grant, 3K USD, PI 2018

2018

2018

2018

2017

Michigan Cambridge Research Initiative, 15K USD, PI

Microsoft Azure Cloud Computing Grant, 25K USD, PI

SRC JUMP grant, 1,25M USD (31.2M USD total), PI

Intel Gift, SysTEX'18 Workshop Sponsorship, 2K USD, PI

# STUDENT AWARDS AND HONORS

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP), Kevin Loughlin	2020
Award for Excellence in Climate, Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion; Univ. of Michigan, Kevin Loughlin	2020
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP), Andrew Loveless	2020
Facebook Fellowship Finalist, Tanvir Ahmed Khan	2020
ACM Student Research Competition First Prize, Nathan Brown	2020

#### EMPLOYMENT

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA Assistant Professor Sep. 2017–present

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

Microsoft Research Cambridge, United Kingdom Researcher Aug. 2016-Aug. 2017

Research on computer systems and networks

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL) Lausanne, Switzerland

Dec. 2015-Jul. 2016 Postdoctoral Researcher

Research on software security

• I developed infrastructure that relies on hardware support to improve software security.

Research Assistant Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Research on software reliability with an emphasis on concurrent software

- I developed **Gist**, the first technique for accurately, efficiently, and automatically diagnosing the root causes of in-production failures, by using a combination of static and dynamic program analysis.
- I developed RaceMob, the first automated in-production data race detection technique that can be kept always-on and provides high accuracy, by combining static data race detection with adaptive, crowdsourced dynamic data race detection.
- I developed Portend, a high-accuracy technique to classify data races according to their potential consequences under arbitrary memory models, by using symbolic program analysis to explore multiple program paths and schedules to determine the effects of data races.
- I developed Bias-Free Sampling, a technique that allows efficient sampling of rarely executed code (where bugs often lurk) without over-sampling frequently executed code, by using a new sampling algorithm and existing hardware support.

Intel Corp. Santa Clara, CA, USA Research Intern Jul. 2015–Sep. 2015

Automated root cause diagnosis of failures and security enhancements using hardware support

- I developed a tool that allows developers to determine which program statements operate on a given data type at runtime using a mix of static program analysis and hardware support. In our experiments, this tool reduces the number of statements to examine during debugging by an order of magnitude. This tool is being extended internally at Intel.
- I began investigating hardware support for enhancing system security, in particular, efficient path profiling for auditing and detecting control flow hijack attacks.

VMware Inc. Palo Alto, CA, USA Research and Development Intern

Automated debugging and runtime control flow tracking

Jun. 2014-Sep. 2014

- I implemented a runtime for efficient control flow tracking in software. This work formed the basis of my **Gist** work on root cause diagnosis.
- I designed and implemented an infrastructure to remotely debug and profile VMware VCenter virtual machine management software, while it is running in production. This infrastructure is used by VCenter developers at VMWare.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA

Research Intern

Jun. 2013–Sep. 2013

Efficient runtime execution sampling technique and low overhead coverage measurement

- I worked on the design of the **Bias-Free Sampling** framework for efficient runtime sampling. I designed and implemented the bias-free sampling framework for managed code (i.e., C#). This tool is internally used at Microsoft.
- I designed and implemented a fault injection tool to detect resource leakage problems using dynamic binary instrumentation.

#### Siemens Corporate Technology

Istanbul, Turkey

Senior Software Engineer

Mar. 2008–May 2010

Embedded home and industrial automation software

• I designed and implemented a real-time embedded gateway software between Siemens communication processors and a building automation system using C++ on top of VxWorks.

#### **Aselsan Electronic Industries**

Ankara, Turkey

Software Engineer

May 2006–Mar. 2008

Embedded motor control and functional testing infrastructure

• I was responsible for a real-time embedded control software for turret motor control. I also designed and implemented a full-system functional testing software using C++ on top of VxWorks for Power PC architectures.

Student Intern Jun. 2005–Jul. 2005

Embedded software development

• I developed embedded control software for a night vision camera using C++ and PIC assembly on a PIC microcontroller.

## PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] DOLMA: Securing Speculation with the Principle of Transient Non-Observability. Kevin Loughlin, Ian Neal, Jicheng Ma, Elisa Tsai, Ofir Weisse, Satish Narayanasamy, and Baris Kasikci. [USENIX Security'21], Vancouver, Canada, August 2021.
- [2] DMon: Efficient Detection and Correction of Data Locality Problems using Selective Profiling. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Ian Neal, Gilles Pokam, Barzan Mozafari, and Baris Kasikci. [OSDI'21], Online, Jul 2021.
- [3] Ripple: Profile-Guided Instruction CacheReplacement for Data Center Applications. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Dexin Zhang, Akshitha Sriraman, Joseph Devietti, Gilles Pokam, Heiner Litz, and Baris Kasikci. [ISCA'21], Worldwide, June 2021.
- [4] Reproducing Production Failures with Execution Reconstruction. Gefei Zuo, Jiacheng Ma, Andrew Quinn, Pramod Bhatotia, and Baris Kasikci. [PLDI'21], June 2021.

- [5] Accelerating Byzantine Fault Tolerance for Real-Time Systems with Eager Execution. Andrew Loveless, Ron Dreslinski, Baris Kasikci, and Linh Phan. [RTAS'21], May 2021.
- [6] Hippocrates: Healing Persistent Memory Bugs Without Doing Any Harm. Ian Neal, Andrew Quinn, and Baris Kasikci. [ASPLOS'21], Detroit, USA, April 2021.
- [7] Rethinking File Mapping Structures for Persistent Memory. Ian Neal, Gefei Zuo, Eric Shiple, Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Youngjin Kwon, Simon Peter, and Baris Kasikci. [FAST'21], February 2021.
- [8] Agamotto: How Persistent is your Persistent Memory Application? Ian Neal, Ben Reeves, Ben Stoler, Andrew Quinn, Youngjin Kwon, Simon Peter, and Baris Kasikci. [OSDI'20], Vancouver, Canada, November 2020.
- [9] I-SPY: Context-Driven Conditional Instruction Prefetching with Coalescing. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Akshitha Sriraman, Joseph Devietti, Gilles Pokam, Heiner Litz, and Baris Kasikci. [MICRO'20], Athens, Greece, October 2020.
- [10] Optimus: A Hypervisor for Shared-Memory FPGA Platforms. Jiacheng Ma, Gefei Zuo, Kevin Loughlin, Xiaohe Cheng, Yanqiang Liu, Abel Mulugeta Eneyew, Zhengwei Qi, and Baris Kasikci. [ASPLOS'20], Lausanne, Switzerland, March 2020.
- [11] CPU Microarchitectural Performance Characterization of Cloud Video Transcoding. Yuhan Chen, Jingyuan Zhu, Tanvir Ahmed Khan, and Baris Kasikci. [IISWC'20], Beijing, China, 2020.
- [12] I4: Incremental Inference of Inductive Invartiants. Haojun Ma, Aman Goel, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Manos Kapritsos, Baris Kasikci, and Karem Sakallah. [SOSP'19], Ontario, Canada, October 2019.
- [13] NDA: Preventing Speculative Execution Attacks at Their Source. Ofir Weisee, Ian Neal, Kevin Loughlin, Thomas Wenisch, and Baris Kasikci. [MICRO'19], Cleaveland, USA, October 2019.
- [14] Huron: Hybrid False Sharing Detection and Repair. Tanvir Ahmed Khan, Yifan Zhao, Gilles Pokam, Barzan Mozafari, and Baris Kasikci. [PLDI'19], Phoenix, USA, June 2019.
- [15] Morpheus: A Vulnerability-Tolerant Secure Architecture Based on Ensembles of Moving Target Defenses with Churn. Mark Gallagher, Lauren Biernacki, Shibo Chen, Zelalem Birhanu Aweke, Salessawi Ferede Yitbarek, Misiker Tadesse Aga, Austin Harris, Zhixing Xu, Baris Kasikci, Valeria Bertacco, Sharad Malik, Mohit Tiwari, and Todd Austin. [ASPLOS'19], Providence, RI, March 2019.
- [16] REPT: Reverse Debugging of Failures in Deployed Software. Xinyang Ge Weidong Cui, Baris Kasikci, Ben Niu, Upamanyu Sharma, Ruoyu Wang, and Insu Yun. [OSDI'18], Carlsbad, USA, October 2018.
- [17] Foreshadow: Extracting the Keys to the Intel SGX Kingdom with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Ofir Weisse, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Thomas F. Wenisch, Yuval Yarom, and Raoul Strackx. [USENIX Security'18], Baltimore, USA, August 2018.
- [18] Cntr: Lightweight OS Containers. Jorg Thalheim, Pramod Bhatotia, Pedro Fonseca, and Baris Kasikci. [USENIX ATC'18], Boston, USA, July 2018.
- [19] Foreshadow-NG: Breaking the Virtual Memory Abstraction with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Ofir Weisse, Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Raoul Strackx, Thomas F. Wenisch, and Yuval Yarom. arXiv'18, 2018.
- [20] Lazy Diagnosis of In-Production Concurrency Bugs. Baris Kasikci, Weidong Cui, Xinyang Ge, and Ben Niu. [SOSP'17], Shanghai, China, October 2017.
- [21] Failure Sketching: A Technique for Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, and George Candea. [SOSP'15], Monterey, CA, October 2015.

- [22] Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, Madanlal Musuvathi, and George Candea. [HotOS'15], Kartause Ittingen, Switzerland, May 2015.
- [23] Automated Classification of Data Races Under Both Strong and Weak Memory Models. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. [TOPLAS'15], May 2015.
- [24] Efficient Tracing of Cold Code Via Bias-Free Sampling. Baris Kasikci, Thomas Ball, George Candea, John Erickson, and Madanlal Musuvathi. [USENIX ATC'14], Philadelphia, PA, June 2014.
- [25] Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs. Ali Kheradmand, Baris Kasikci, and George Candea. /WODET'14/, Salt Lake City, UT, March 2014.
- [26] RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. [SOSP'13], Farmington, PA, November 2013.
- [27] Automated Debugging for Arbitrarily Long Executions. Cristian Zamfir, Baris Kasikci, Johannes Kinder, Edouard Bugnion, and George Candea. [HotOS'13], Santa Ana Pueblo, NM, May 2013.
- [28] CORD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. [HotDep'12], Hollywood, CA, October 2012.
- [29] Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. [ASPLOS'12], London, UK, March 2012.
- [30] Scalable Modeling of Software Product Line Variability. Baris Kasikci and Semih Bilgen. [SPLC'09], San Francisco, CA, August 2009.

#### TAIKS

TALKS	
Eliminating Speculative Execution Vulnerabilities	
• DARPA (Invited Talk)	$\mathrm{Sep}\ 2019$
Towards Continuous In-Production Failure Diagnosis	
• Ohio State University (Invited Talk)	July 2018
• Greater Chicago Area Systems Research Workshop, University of Chicago (Invited Talk)	May 2018
• Purdue University (Invited Talk)	May 2018
Hardware-Software Co-Design for Debugging and Performance Anlysis	
• Workshop on Resilient Systems, TU Dresden (Keynote)	Apr. 2017
Symbolic Execution: A Gentle Introduction	
• Cyber In Bretagne Summer School (Invited Talk)	Jul. 2016
Stamping Out Concurrency Bugs	
• Royal Holloway, University of London, Seminar	Apr. 2016
• Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar	Apr. 2016
• Carnegie Mellon University, Seminar	Apr. 2016
• University of Southern California, Seminar	Mar. 2016
• University of Rochester, Seminar	Mar. 2016
• Microsoft Research Redmond, Seminar	Mar. 2016
• Microsoft Research Cambridge, Seminar	Mar. 2016
• MPI Software Systems, Seminar	Mar. 2016
• University College London, Seminar	Mar. 2016

• Rice University, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• University of Toronto, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• University of Michigan, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• Boston University, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• VMWare Research, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• University of British Columbia, Seminar	Feb.	2016
• Simon Fraser University, Seminar		2016
Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures		
• Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP)	Oct.	2015
• Intel Corp.	Sep.	2015
• Google	Sep.	2015
• VMware Inc.	Sep.	2015
Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug	•	
• EcoCloud Annual Event	Jun.	2015
• Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	May	2015
Efficient Tracing of Cold Code via Bias-Free Sampling		
• USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC)	$\operatorname{Jun}$ .	2014
Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs		
• Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet)	Mar.	2014
RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection.		
• Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP)	Oct.	2013
• EPFL Systems Seminar	Oct.	2013
CoRD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection		
• Workshop on Hot Topics in System Dependability (HotDep)	Oct.	2012
Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend		
<ul> <li>International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)</li> </ul>	Mar.	2012
How to Build Reliable Software?		
• Seminar talk to the incoming undergraduate students at EPFL	Sep.	2011
Professional Service		
PC Chair		
Workshop on Hot Topics In Operating Systems (HotOS)		2021
EuroSys Doctoral Workshop (Euro'DW)		2021
International Conference on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE)		2020 <b>PC</b>
Workshop on System Software for Trusted Execution (SysTEX) (co-located with CCS'18) Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC) Poster Session		2018 2018

# Member

Symp. on Operating System Design and Implementation (OSDI) Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP) Intl Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems 2022	2021, 2020 2019 s (ASPLOS) 2021,
EuroSys	2019, 2021
Intl. Conf. on Virtual Execution Environments (VEE)	2019, 2021
Intl. Conf. on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS)	2019,2017
EuroSys Roger Needham PhD Award Committee	2019
EuroSys Doctoral Workshop (EuroDW)	2018
Symp. on Cloud Computing (SoCC)	2018
World Wide Web Conference (WWW)	2017
Intl. Symp. on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA), Artifact Evaluation Committee	2014
Journal Reviewer	
Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization	2018
Transactions on Software Engineering	2015
Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology	2015
Extended Review Committee	0001
Intl. Symp. on Microarchitecture (MICRO) Intl. Symp. on Computer Architecture (ISCA)	2021 2021
Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating System	
Shadow PC Member	
EuroSys Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2013, 2015
External Reviewer	
Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)	2011. 2013
EuroSys Conf. on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2011, 2012
USENIX Annual Technical Conf. (USENIX ATC)	2011
Intl. Conf. on Compiler Construction (CC)	2017
Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	2011, 2013
Conf. on Innovative Data Systems Research (CIDR)	2013
Intl. Conf. on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN) Symposium on Cloud Computing (SOCC)	2011, 2013 2012
Intl. SPIN Workshop on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)	2012
Committee Member	
EPFL Doctoral School of Computer and Communication Sciences Audit Committee	2015
TEACHING	
Introduction to Operating Systems (EECS 482) (undergrad level, University of Mic	, ,
Advanced Operating Systems (EECS 582) (grad level, University of Michigan)	2017, 2019, 2020
RESEARCH MENTORING	

Jan 2018–

PhD

Tanvir Ahmed Khan

Kevin Loughlin Andrew Loveless Jiacheng Ma Ian Neal Ofir Weisse Gefei Zuo Marina Minkin Andrew Quinn	Sep 2018– Sep 2018– Sep 2018– Sep 2018– Sep 2017–May 2020 Sep 2018– Sep 2020– Feb 2021–
Master's Nathan Brown (ACM Student Research Competition Winner) Muhammed Ugur	Sep 2019– Jan 2021–

Muhammed Ugur Undergraduate

Dexin Zhang
Shixin Song

May 2020–
Feb 2021–

## Alumni

Ben Stoler  $MSc \rightarrow UCSD PhD, 2021$ Yineng Yan  $MSc \rightarrow UT$  Austin PhD, 2021 Morgan Borjigin-Wang  $BSc \rightarrow Michigan MSc, 2020$ Zhiqi Chen  $BSc \rightarrow CMU MSc, 2020$ Yongwei Yuan  $BSc \rightarrow Purdue PhD, 2020$ Ruiyang Zhu  $BSc \rightarrow Michigan PhD, 2020$ Elisa Tsai  $BSc \rightarrow Michigan PhD, 2020$ Ben Reeves  $MSc \rightarrow Qumulo, 2020$ Ofir Weisse  $PhD \rightarrow Google, 2020$  $BSc \rightarrow MIT PhD, 2020$ Upamanyu Sharma Yimeng Zhou  $\mathrm{BSc} \to \mathrm{Google},\, 2020$  $BSc \rightarrow Google, 2019$ Xiaohe Cheng John Wu  $MSc \rightarrow Apple, 2019$ Liran Xiao  $BSc \rightarrow UCLA MSc, 2019$ Yifan Dai  $BSc \rightarrow University of Wisconsin PhD, 2019$ Yifan Zhao  $BSc \rightarrow UIUC PhD, 2019$ 

### LANGUAGES

English: fluent French: fluent Turkish: native German: beginner

## References

Available upon request